<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[PFWiki]]></title><description><![CDATA[Obsidian digital garden]]></description><link>http://github.com/dylang/node-rss</link><image><url>site-lib/media/favicon.png</url><title>PFWiki</title><link></link></image><generator>Webpage HTML Export plugin for Obsidian</generator><lastBuildDate>Fri, 25 Jul 2025 14:26:43 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="site-lib/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><pubDate>Fri, 25 Jul 2025 14:26:39 GMT</pubDate><ttl>60</ttl><dc:creator></dc:creator><item><title><![CDATA[PFWiki]]></title><description><![CDATA[This is an open-source documentation of an approach towards <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="sustainability" data-href="sustainability" href="terms/sustainability.html#_0" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Sustainable</a> design, distribution and production of <a data-href="artifacts" href="terms/artifacts.html#_0" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">artifacts</a> for <a data-href="personal fabrication" href="terms/personal-fabrication.html#_0" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">personal fabrication</a>. In this documentation not only this approach will be described but also the foundation of this approach based in academic research and testing.As this research is currently in its starting phase and still ongoing much of the information within this documentation is subject to drastic change.<br>This documentation was created in <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://obsidian.md/" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://obsidian.md/" target="_self">Obsidian</a> converted to a web compatible format using <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://docs.obsidianweb.net/features/dataview.html" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://docs.obsidianweb.net/features/dataview.html" target="_self">Obsidian Webpage HTML Export</a> and hosted using <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://github.io/" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://github.io/" target="_self">Github</a> from the <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://github.com/FransTW/PMWiki" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://github.com/FransTW/PMWiki" target="_self">FransTW/PFWiki</a> repository.Project proposal
<br><a data-href="Assignment direction ideation" href="notes/project-proposal/assignment-direction-ideation.html#_0" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Assignment direction ideation</a>
<br><a data-href="Initial assignment description" href="notes/project-proposal/initial-assignment-description.html#_0" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Initial assignment description</a>
Sources
<br><a data-href="kara2022" href="sources/kara2022/kara2022.html#_0" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">kara2022</a>
<br><a data-href="kohtala2015" href="sources/kohtala2015/kohtala2015.html#_0" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">kohtala2015</a>
<br><a data-href="kohtala2015a" href="sources/kohtala2015a/kohtala2015a.html#_0" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">kohtala2015a</a>
]]></description><link>pfwiki.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">PFWiki.md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 25 Jul 2025 13:47:39 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Assignment direction ideation]]></title><description><![CDATA[Creating a framework for designing open-source sustainable products for local personal production. Defing standards:
Materials Bulk (CNC, Lasercutting)
Fastners
Glue?
Plastics (3D printing)
Metal Manufacturing methods CNC
Lasercutting
3D printing metal
plastic
powder Software/file usage
Assembly
Possiblities for individual customization
Safety
Possibilities of automating design the process to set standards
CAD which limits design to production methods and available materials most efficient flat layout generation (nesting generator)
FEM analysis for safety (standardized and easy interface for FEM testing) Automatic/supported instuction generation with difficultie ratings of assembly
Automatic cost estimation Database Automatic PLC impact analysis Database Design for DIY
Design for maintanance
Open-source design
Personal fabrication
Local production
Sustainable design
(2022) Enabling Personal Fabrication for a Sustainable Built Environment.Uma chair
<a rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://dextop.co/ma-chair-assembly-guide/" target="_self">https://dextop.co/ma-chair-assembly-guide/</a>]]></description><link>notes/project-proposal/assignment-direction-ideation.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Notes/Project proposal/Assignment direction ideation.md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 25 Jul 2025 11:11:31 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Initial assignment description]]></title><description><![CDATA[Internal Research Assignment
Master IDE Graduation ProjectSupervisors: Jairo da Costa
Contact: <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="mailto:j.dacosta@utwente.nl" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href=".html" target="_self">j.dacosta@utwente.nl</a><br>
Research Group: Interaction Design (<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://www.utwente.nl/en/et/dpm/chair/id/%5D(https://www.utwente.nl/en/et/dpm/chair/id/)" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://www.utwente.nl/en/et/dpm/chair/id/%5D(https://www.utwente.nl/en/et/dpm/chair/id/)" target="_self">https://www.utwente.nl/en/et/dpm/chair/id/](https://www.utwente.nl/en/et/dpm/chair/id/)</a>)
Collaboration: Dr. Rosangela Tenorio, University of Western Australia (UWA), Bio-based Materials Design Lab<br>In recent years, advances in ICT, including desktop manufacturing technologies, have enabled the implementation of circular and distributed production systems on an unprecedented scale. Making distributed production feasible through <a data-href="digital fabrication technologies" href=".html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">digital fabrication technologies</a> can facilitate models of production and consumption that are more sustainable, promote citizen engagement, and facilitate disruptive innovation through technological <a data-href="leapfrogging" href="terms/leapfrogging.html#_0" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">leapfrogging</a>. However, promising as it may be, fostering distributed production through personal fabrication is not inherently sustainable. In fact, democratising access to digital fabrication and disseminating Maker Culture through internet-based networks of collaborative knowledge will increase material consumption, artefact production, and waste disposal. For instance, through practices like product customisation and personal fabrication, citizens have increased their ability to affect ‘what’, ‘how’, and ‘how many’ artefacts are produced. This raises the question: How can citizens in resource-poor or constrained contexts be enabled to create sustainable solutions through personal fabrication practices?<br>This transdisciplinary project combines sustainable design engineering, <a data-href="grassroots innovation" href="terms/grassroots-innovation.html#_0" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">grassroots innovation</a>, <a data-href="appropriate technology" href="terms/appropriate-technology.html#_0" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">appropriate technology</a>, and <a data-href="citizen science" href=".html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">citizen science</a>. It explores how emerging technologies, such as digital fabrication, augmented reality, and AI tools, combined with locally available knowledge and inexpensive resources, converge to empower people in the transition to decentralised, equitable, and sustainable production systems. The project aims to develop an online platform for <a data-href="open-source appropriate technologies" href="terms/open-source-appropriate-technologies.html#_0" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">open-source appropriate technologies</a> (<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="open-source appropriate technologies" data-href="open-source appropriate technologies" href="terms/open-source-appropriate-technologies.html#_0" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">OSAT</a>) and personal fabrication processes that are compatible with citizens’ resources, knowledge, and skill levels, particularly in vulnerable and underserved populations. This platform will enable self-fabricated solutions through a combination of digital and physical construction processes. The project’s outcomes will include an online platform for sustainable personal fabrication, revised OSAT prototypes, assembly, manufacturing, and upcycling manuals, as well as augmented experiences.Notes: The results of this project will be available open-source and submitted to the Distributed Design Awards 2026 and Dutch Design Week 2026.<br>This is a collaborative effort with <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://research-repository.uwa.edu.au/en/persons/00097167" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://research-repository.uwa.edu.au/en/persons/00097167" target="_self">Dr. Rosangela Tenorio</a>, an Associate Professor of Architecture at the University of Western Australia (UWA), along with the team from the <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://bbmdesignlab.com/" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://bbmdesignlab.com/" target="_self">Bio-based Materials Design Lab</a>. The project aims to develop an online personal fabrication platform that educates citizens by co-designing and creating nature-based solutions addressing global environmental challenges through local, sustainable making. The platform will be closely connected to the <a data-href="BBMLab Camp" href=".html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">BBMLab Camp</a>. The BBMLAB Camp comprises a series of micro-credentials tailored for individuals who have completed a Bachelor’s Degree and are eager to learn about the application of biomaterials in design through desktop manufacturing technologies, particularly in engaging with climate action through sustainable production and consumption within the contexts of architecture and product design. The BBMLab Camp program empowers citizens to actively contribute to the transition towards alternative production and consumption systems by providing learning resources and a platform that enhances sustainability in open-source resources, customises solutions to local contexts, and fosters knowledge sharing between makers and the broader community. Furthermore, it involves the continuous development of innovative, sustainable, open-source products and resources for learning, such as <a data-href="circular furniture" href=".html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">circular furniture</a>, <a data-href="blue-green panels" href=".html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">blue-green panels</a>, and making and <a data-href="upcycling manuals" href=".html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">upcycling manuals</a>.<br>Da Costa, J., Junior, Tenorio, R., &amp; Santos, A. D. (2022). Enabling personal fabrication for a sustainable built environment. In Elsevier eBooks (pp. 473–483). <a rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://doi.org/10.1016/b978-0-323-90386-8.00037-1" target="_self">https://doi.org/10.1016/b978-0-323-90386-8.00037-1</a>Tenorio, R., &amp; da Costa Junior, J.&nbsp;(Eds.) (2022).&nbsp;SPECTACLE: Bio-Based Materials Design Lab 2019-2021 works. (1 ed.) (Bio-Based Materials Design Lab Series). The University of Western Australia.<br>Johansson, A., Kisch, P., &amp; Mirata, M. (2005). Distributed economies – A new engine for innovation. Journal of Cleaner Production, 13(10–11), 971–979. <a rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jclepro.2004.12.015" target="_self">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jclepro.2004.12.015</a><br><a data-href="kohtala2015" href="sources/kohtala2015/kohtala2015.html#_0" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">kohtala2015</a>N. Gershenfeld. (2012) “How to Make Almost Anything: The Digital Fabrication Revolution,” Foreign Affairs, vol. 91, no. 6, pp. 43–57, 2012.<br><a data-href="kohtala2015a" href="sources/kohtala2015a/kohtala2015a.html#_0" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">kohtala2015a</a>Case Studies<br>
Distributed Design - <a rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://distributeddesign.eu/" target="_self">https://distributeddesign.eu/</a><br>
Open Desk Furniture - <a rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://www.opendesk.cc/" target="_self">https://www.opendesk.cc/</a><br>
Wiki Factory - <a rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://wikifactory.com/community/projects" target="_self">https://wikifactory.com/community/projects</a><br>
WikiHouse - <a rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://www.wikihouse.cc/" target="_self">https://www.wikihouse.cc/</a>Pilot Project (this project)<br>
Uma Chair Digital Assembly Guide - <a rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://bbmdesignlab.com/uma-chair-assembly-guide" target="_self">https://bbmdesignlab.com/uma-chair-assembly-guide</a>Note: AR experience available on mobile only.]]></description><link>notes/project-proposal/initial-assignment-description.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Notes/Project proposal/Initial assignment description.md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 25 Jul 2025 11:11:29 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Project proposal]]></title><description><![CDATA[
<a data-href="Assignment direction ideation" href="notes/project-proposal/assignment-direction-ideation.html#_0" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Assignment direction ideation</a>
<br><a data-href="Initial assignment description" href="notes/project-proposal/initial-assignment-description.html#_0" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Initial assignment description</a>
]]></description><link>notes/project-proposal/project-proposal.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Notes/Project proposal/Project proposal.md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 25 Jul 2025 11:11:27 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[kara2022]]></title><description><![CDATA[The global society faces an existential threat if it fails to meet current and future material needs of its populations, while staying within the carrying capacity of our planet. An approach that has been put forwards to address this complex challenge is to aim to close our society's material flows through introduction of a Circular Economy (CE). This paper provides an extensive literature review to understand the evolution of material circularity concepts and strategies, and their potential for increasing material efficiency and reduce environmental impacts towards meeting the material needs of our societies in an environmentally sustainable manner. Based on the review it can be concluded that CE may have a strong potential to help address the challenge. However, this requires broadening the focus of CE from technical and economical to political and socio-cultural dimensions, adopting a whole-systems approach, aiming to redesign economic and social relations to not just reduce the impact humanity has on the environment but actually achieve a balance in human-nature relations with a planetary boundary thinking. Pursuing purely technical and economic avenues to implement CE for increasing material circulation and sustainable growth on the foundation of our current linear economic system, will not achieve its full potential. It will not be sustainable but continue to produce the challenges that we currently have.Kara, S., Hauschild, M., Sutherland, J., &amp; McAloone, T. (2022). Closed-loop systems to circular economy: A pathway to environmental sustainability? CIRP Annals, 71(2), 505–528. <a rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cirp.2022.05.008" target="_self">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cirp.2022.05.008</a><br>In most instances, sustainability is shown in the middle supported by all three elements as enablers. These models have emerged to be one of the most dominant forms of explaining sustainability and sustainable development framework over the past three decades and are frequently used in literature, online works, business models and documentation of sustainability, and they were the foundation of the triple bottom line concept for corporate sustainability (<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="zotero://open-pdf/library/items/VVGQYZWX?page=2&amp;annotation=BSFDDWTA" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="zotero:/open-pdf/library/items/VVGQYZWX?page=2&amp;annotation=BSFDDWTA" target="_self">2</a>)<br> <img alt="Sources/kara2022/attachments/kara2022-2-x295-y305.png" src="sources/kara2022/attachments/kara2022-2-x295-y305.png" target="_self">]]></description><link>sources/kara2022/kara2022.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Sources/kara2022/kara2022.md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 25 Jul 2025 11:11:23 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="sources/kara2022/attachments/kara2022-2-x295-y305.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;sources/kara2022/attachments/kara2022-2-x295-y305.png&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[kohtala2015]]></title><description><![CDATA[This paper presents an integrated literature review on how the environmental sustainability of distributed production is studied in a variety of disciplinary sources. The notion of distributed production suggests an alternative to mass production that differs in scale, location and consumer–producer relationship. Understanding its environmental implications (and thereby dematerialization potential) is regarded pertinent and timely. Key themes in the review included how distributed production can promote product longevity and closed material loops, as well as localizing production. New and closer ties between producer and consumer seemed central discussions but were underdeveloped with regard to sustainability potential. Empirical work was seen especially in research on Additive Manufacturing Processes, while the bulk of the studies were conceptual explorations with little testing in the real world as yet. This affirms the emerging nature of the topic and points to a clear need for more (and more diverse) empirical research. The review summarizes the opportunities for greater environmental sustainability as well as potential threats that could serve to guide and improve these novel practices today. It sets the stage for ‘distributed production’ to be examined as its own phenomenon by proposing how it can be characterized and suggests that a research agenda could build upon the work initiated here.Kohtala, C. (2015). Addressing sustainability in research on distributed production: An integrated literature review. Journal of Cleaner Production, 106, 654–668. <a rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jclepro.2014.09.039" target="_self">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jclepro.2014.09.039</a><br>The notion of “distributed economies” promotes small-scale, flexible networks of local socio-economic actors using local resources according to local needs, in the spirit of sustainable development (Johansson et al., 2005). (<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="zotero://open-pdf/library/items/4RMPYD29?page=2&amp;annotation=VVGSN7D8" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="zotero:/open-pdf/library/items/4RMPYD29?page=2&amp;annotation=VVGSN7D8" target="_self">2</a>)<br>“prosumption” and the consumer a “prosumer” (Toffler, 1980), for whom production becomes part of the consumption process. When prosumption involves peer-to-peer networks, some re- searchers refer to the practice as “commons-based peer produc- tion” (Benkler, 2006). (<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="zotero://open-pdf/library/items/4RMPYD29?page=2&amp;annotation=6K95YMDD" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="zotero:/open-pdf/library/items/4RMPYD29?page=2&amp;annotation=6K95YMDD" target="_self">2</a>)what fields, disciplines or specialists are discussing distribute
production and how they are addressing it how sustainability is represented and the nature of the rel
tionship between environmental sustainability and distribut
production; a
what research gaps currently exist as well as what resea h<br>
directions are most promisi . (<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="zotero://open-pdf/library/items/4RMPYD29?page=2&amp;annotation=DVXZ4NB4" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="zotero:/open-pdf/library/items/4RMPYD29?page=2&amp;annotation=DVXZ4NB4" target="_self">2</a>)<br> <img alt="Sources/kohtala2015/attachments/kohtala2015-3-x43-y94.png" src="sources/kohtala2015/attachments/kohtala2015-3-x43-y94.png" target="_self"> maybe interesting to note possible differences in consumption behavior between "on demand" production and mass production.
<br>Nearly all authors lamented the lack of research in this area: studies that would validate the claim that AM technologies are more environmentally benign than conventional manufacturing methods in terms of waste, energy, material use, emissions and so on. (<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="zotero://open-pdf/library/items/4RMPYD29?page=5&amp;annotation=HQABWNNW" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="zotero:/open-pdf/library/items/4RMPYD29?page=5&amp;annotation=HQABWNNW" target="_self">5</a>)<br>the trade-off between high environmental impact per unit in small volumes and low impacts per unit but in mass quantities. This also entails the challenge to identify the most sensible comparison point and system boundaries. (<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="zotero://open-pdf/library/items/4RMPYD29?page=5&amp;annotation=ZYGDSMFH" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="zotero:/open-pdf/library/items/4RMPYD29?page=5&amp;annotation=ZYGDSMFH" target="_self">5</a>)<br>Aside from toxicity during use, the authors pointed to the disposal and post-processing stages as problematic because of the materials' unknown properties. (<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="zotero://open-pdf/library/items/4RMPYD29?page=5&amp;annotation=7L24KV4A" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="zotero:/open-pdf/library/items/4RMPYD29?page=5&amp;annotation=7L24KV4A" target="_self">5</a>)<br>focused on the post-use stage, which they regar- ded as under-addressed, in a conceptual exploration on closing MC resource loops. (<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="zotero://open-pdf/library/items/4RMPYD29?page=5&amp;annotation=SM3EDZHH" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="zotero:/open-pdf/library/items/4RMPYD29?page=5&amp;annotation=SM3EDZHH" target="_self">5</a>)<br>Medini et al. (2011) [17-MCPC] aimed to map the MC enterprise's interrelationships with the external environments (<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="zotero://open-pdf/library/items/4RMPYD29?page=5&amp;annotation=4QJW8G9B" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="zotero:/open-pdf/library/items/4RMPYD29?page=5&amp;annotation=4QJW8G9B" target="_self">5</a>)<br>Corti et al. (2011) [6-MCPC] proposed a “sustainable mass customized reference framework”, setting out the (interdependent) steps involved in product, production system and supply chain design. (<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="zotero://open-pdf/library/items/4RMPYD29?page=5&amp;annotation=ZI44GEMU" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="zotero:/open-pdf/library/items/4RMPYD29?page=5&amp;annotation=ZI44GEMU" target="_self">5</a>)<br>Sakao et al. (2005) [24-MCPC] proposed that sustainability must be tackled earlier on in the design process if dematerialization is a goal, describing a tool aimed to help planners focus more on “customer value”. (<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="zotero://open-pdf/library/items/4RMPYD29?page=5&amp;annotation=WPYMKDIC" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="zotero:/open-pdf/library/items/4RMPYD29?page=5&amp;annotation=WPYMKDIC" target="_self">5</a>)<br>Wijekoon and Badurdeen (2011) [29-MCPC] and Letmathe (2003) [14-MCPC] suggested that quantifying factors offers managers better strategic tools for evaluation and application. In the former, the model incorporated a wide set of performance metrics for a sustainable MC business model. (<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="zotero://open-pdf/library/items/4RMPYD29?page=5&amp;annotation=9DLUTWZ9" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="zotero:/open-pdf/library/items/4RMPYD29?page=5&amp;annotation=9DLUTWZ9" target="_self">5</a>)<br>little or no testing reported (<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="zotero://open-pdf/library/items/4RMPYD29?page=5&amp;annotation=A2KGG667" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="zotero:/open-pdf/library/items/4RMPYD29?page=5&amp;annotation=A2KGG667" target="_self">5</a>)
take this into account before reading the papers.
<br>For Diegel et al. (2010) [8-JSD], in a conceptual article, envi- ronmental sustainability is better ensured when designers follow eco-design principles but also strive to create “lasting objects of desire, pleasure and attachment” (<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="zotero://open-pdf/library/items/4RMPYD29?page=5&amp;annotation=MZ6K8R7Z" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="zotero:/open-pdf/library/items/4RMPYD29?page=5&amp;annotation=MZ6K8R7Z" target="_self">5</a>)<br>AM is also highly suited to customizing products according to “customer needs” (which were unspecified here). This potentially leads to a greater attachment to the product which will therefore be used longer and not thrown away prematurely (<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="zotero://open-pdf/library/items/4RMPYD29?page=5&amp;annotation=6EBDDGZU" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="zotero:/open-pdf/library/items/4RMPYD29?page=5&amp;annotation=6EBDDGZU" target="_self">5</a>)<br>“co-creation”, where “design experiences” matter as much as a well-designed garment in their conceptual exploratory paper. (<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="zotero://open-pdf/library/items/4RMPYD29?page=6&amp;annotation=NNU8BQ8S" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="zotero:/open-pdf/library/items/4RMPYD29?page=6&amp;annotation=NNU8BQ8S" target="_self">6</a>)<br>For Steffen and Gros (2003) [26-MCPC], digital fabrication (of furniture) as local, distributed production was hypothesized to support sustained employment and regional development while avoiding transportation impacts (<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="zotero://open-pdf/library/items/4RMPYD29?page=6&amp;annotation=TB2MQY7K" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="zotero:/open-pdf/library/items/4RMPYD29?page=6&amp;annotation=TB2MQY7K" target="_self">6</a>)<br>Fogliatto et al. (2012) [11-IJPE] presented a widely cited literature review on mass customization (<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="zotero://open-pdf/library/items/4RMPYD29?page=6&amp;annotation=JUKNNZM3" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="zotero:/open-pdf/library/items/4RMPYD29?page=6&amp;annotation=JUKNNZM3" target="_self">6</a>)<br>Fox and Li (2012) [12-TFSC], whose framework for roadmapping material technologies was aimed especially at entrepreneurs and regional development au- thorities, to better determine what technologies support “sustain- able” prosumption practices. A key issue for the authors was the localization of production and materials that corresponds with lower transport emissions. (<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="zotero://open-pdf/library/items/4RMPYD29?page=6&amp;annotation=FNZZ9I9A" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="zotero:/open-pdf/library/items/4RMPYD29?page=6&amp;annotation=FNZZ9I9A" target="_self">6</a>)<br>in Manzini (2009) [15-DS] (as “distributed systems” of production) and Pearce et al. (2010) [22-JSD] (referring to 3D printing technologies and Fab Labs). In both papers fabbing or peer production was seen as a way to empower local communities and encourage responsible use of local resources (<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="zotero://open-pdf/library/items/4RMPYD29?page=6&amp;annotation=HCTJ7XGH" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="zotero:/open-pdf/library/items/4RMPYD29?page=6&amp;annotation=HCTJ7XGH" target="_self">6</a>)<br>extending product life spans, sug- gesting how to combat psychological obsolescence by design via personalization. (<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="zotero://open-pdf/library/items/4RMPYD29?page=6&amp;annotation=LD2S3VYR" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="zotero:/open-pdf/library/items/4RMPYD29?page=6&amp;annotation=LD2S3VYR" target="_self">6</a>)<br>how end-of-life (EOL) can best be tackled in the mass customizer's business model and how personalization both enables and problematizes recovery. (<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="zotero://open-pdf/library/items/4RMPYD29?page=6&amp;annotation=LD6PQC5J" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="zotero:/open-pdf/library/items/4RMPYD29?page=6&amp;annotation=LD6PQC5J" target="_self">6</a>)<br>emphasized the importance of stronger communicative and “learning” relationships between consumer and producer in MC (<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="zotero://open-pdf/library/items/4RMPYD29?page=6&amp;annotation=LR5ST2D7" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="zotero:/open-pdf/library/items/4RMPYD29?page=6&amp;annotation=LR5ST2D7" target="_self">6</a>)<br>The notion of Product-Service System (PSS), where the consumer is offered a function rather than a product in order to optimize resource use (Mont, 2002), was seen by several authors as a solution to these conundrums: a way to establish the business case for closing loops by personalizing the customer satisfaction rather than the product. (<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="zotero://open-pdf/library/items/4RMPYD29?page=6&amp;annotation=PCGX9845" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="zotero:/open-pdf/library/items/4RMPYD29?page=6&amp;annotation=PCGX9845" target="_self">6</a>)<br>there is ample room for more research and practical in- terventions to test the hypotheses the authors raised. Empirical evidence validating our commonly held assumption that product attachment can have a positive effect on consumption patterns and material flow (i.e. absolute dematerialization) would also be beneficial. (<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="zotero://open-pdf/library/items/4RMPYD29?page=7&amp;annotation=LB8GLKS6" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="zotero:/open-pdf/library/items/4RMPYD29?page=7&amp;annotation=LB8GLKS6" target="_self">7</a>)
what is consumer attitude towards PSS or subscription culture and how to ensure companies don't exploit consumers trough these systems? An ethical approach will be needed to win consumer trust and ensure sustainability.
<br>highlighting the need to incorporate eco-conscious choices in the product configurator or consider sustainability in the co-creation planning. This explicitly aimed not only to inform the consumer about e.g. environmental impacts in production and/or use, but also to allow both sustain- ability constraints and consumer need dictate what is actually produced as opposed to what is merely customized (<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="zotero://open-pdf/library/items/4RMPYD29?page=7&amp;annotation=6KITLFCY" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="zotero:/open-pdf/library/items/4RMPYD29?page=7&amp;annotation=6KITLFCY" target="_self">7</a>)<br>[21-JCP] described a wide range of co-design options, which in turn implied a variety of ways producers, designers and consumers can share both environmental information and responsible decision-making, including what is produced (<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="zotero://open-pdf/library/items/4RMPYD29?page=7&amp;annotation=S2Y4D5II" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="zotero:/open-pdf/library/items/4RMPYD29?page=7&amp;annotation=S2Y4D5II" target="_self">7</a>)
I feel like this is a limited view of the benefits. Not considering deskilling, societal resiliance, jobs, repair, power grid and consumption behaviour base on the triple bottom line.<br>
<img alt="Sources/kohtala2015/attachments/kohtala2015-8-x42-y56.png" src="sources/kohtala2015/attachments/kohtala2015-8-x42-y56.png" target="_self"> <img alt="Sources/kohtala2015/attachments/kohtala2015-8-x311-y67.png" src="sources/kohtala2015/attachments/kohtala2015-8-x311-y67.png" target="_self"><br>
There is hence need for discussion on the valuing systems behind distributed production activities involving material goods. This would serve practical, operational objectives and clarify the axiological underpinnings. (<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="zotero://open-pdf/library/items/4RMPYD29?page=9&amp;annotation=3DC4LZNV" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="zotero:/open-pdf/library/items/4RMPYD29?page=9&amp;annotation=3DC4LZNV" target="_self">9</a>)
<br>Because of the heavy emphasis on frameworks and iden- tifying environmental benefits, combined with the lack of, for instance, real-life case studies, the environmental harms (poten- tially) concomitant with a decentralized production paradigm remained unacknowledged. (<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="zotero://open-pdf/library/items/4RMPYD29?page=12&amp;annotation=DWY6EF8E" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="zotero:/open-pdf/library/items/4RMPYD29?page=12&amp;annotation=DWY6EF8E" target="_self">12</a>)<br>the more exposed the individual becomes to materials and processes and their as yet unknown properties such as toxicity (<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="zotero://open-pdf/library/items/4RMPYD29?page=12&amp;annotation=IMFVETC4" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="zotero:/open-pdf/library/items/4RMPYD29?page=12&amp;annotation=IMFVETC4" target="_self">12</a>)
How about fab labs (and others)? In these spaces safety can be regulated and measured.
<br>The fabrication of new types of products may additionally render them less amenable to existing consumer recycling systems (<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="zotero://open-pdf/library/items/4RMPYD29?page=12&amp;annotation=BM79NVLM" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="zotero:/open-pdf/library/items/4RMPYD29?page=12&amp;annotation=BM79NVLM" target="_self">12</a>)<br>it is possible the production, storage and distribution of materials and components (and their inherent impacts) remain just as invisible to the consumer as the current mass production supply chain is. (<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="zotero://open-pdf/library/items/4RMPYD29?page=12&amp;annotation=MB6RZLYV" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="zotero:/open-pdf/library/items/4RMPYD29?page=12&amp;annotation=MB6RZLYV" target="_self">12</a>)
smaller supply chain and local production may give more controll and transparancy of suppliers. Possibly even trough regulations.<br>
<img alt="Sources/kohtala2015/attachments/kohtala2015-12-x309-y71.png" src="sources/kohtala2015/attachments/kohtala2015-12-x309-y71.png" target="_self">
]]></description><link>sources/kohtala2015/kohtala2015.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Sources/kohtala2015/kohtala2015.md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 25 Jul 2025 11:11:18 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="sources/kohtala2015/attachments/kohtala2015-3-x43-y94.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;sources/kohtala2015/attachments/kohtala2015-3-x43-y94.png&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[kohtala2015a]]></title><description><![CDATA[Distributed manufacturing is rapidly proliferating to citizen level via the use of digital fabrication equipment, especially in dedicated “makerspaces”. The sustainability benefits of citizens' personal fabrication are commonly endorsed. However, to assess how these maker practitioners actually deal with environmental issues, these practitioners and their practices need to be studied. Moreover research on the environmental issues in personal fabrication is nascent despite the common perception that the digital technologies can become disruptive. The present paper is the first to report on how practitioners assess the environmental sustainability of future practices in this rapidly changing field. It does so through an envisioning workshop with leading-edge makers. The findings show that these makers are well able to envision the future of their field. Roughly 25% of the issues covered had clear environmental implications. Within these, issues of energy use, recycling, reusing and reducing materials were covered widely by environmentally-oriented participants. In contrast, issues related to emerging technologies, materials and practices were covered by other participants, but their environmental implications remained unaddressed. The authors concluded there is a gap between different maker subcultures in their sustainability orientations and competences. Further research on the environmental aspects of real-life maker practices and personal fabrication technologies now could help avert negative impacts later, as the maker phenomenon spreads. This knowledge should also be directed to developing targeted environmental guidelines and solutions for personal fabrication users, which are currently lacking. Potential also lies in seeking to enhance dialogue between pro-environmental and new-technology-oriented practitioners through shared spaces, workshops and conferences.Kohtala, C., &amp; Hyysalo, S. (2015). Anticipated environmental sustainability of personal fabrication. Journal of Cleaner Production, 99, 333–344. <a rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jclepro.2015.02.093" target="_self">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jclepro.2015.02.093</a><br>What issues do competent maker practitioners foresee in the environmental sustainability of near future makerspaces? (<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="zotero://open-pdf/library/items/44X7R4CI?page=2&amp;annotation=Q8V5BTG4" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="zotero:/open-pdf/library/items/44X7R4CI?page=2&amp;annotation=Q8V5BTG4" target="_self">2</a>)
Research question of this paper.
<br>Shared makerspaces are workshops with low-cost digital fabrication equipment, typically milling machines for making circuits or casting moulds (using wood, silicon, wax and plaster); vinyl cutters; desktop 3D printers (typically using ABS and PLA plastics); laser cutters (for usually plywood, cardboard and acrylic); and often electronics workstations for microprocessor programming and project prototyping. (<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="zotero://open-pdf/library/items/44X7R4CI?page=2&amp;annotation=RHLTEQQ5" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="zotero:/open-pdf/library/items/44X7R4CI?page=2&amp;annotation=RHLTEQQ5" target="_self">2</a>)<br>Product designs (often shared digitally) are realised by the users themselves and, due to their digital form, can be designed together with peers in other locations. (<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="zotero://open-pdf/library/items/44X7R4CI?page=2&amp;annotation=5CPNESYX" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="zotero:/open-pdf/library/items/44X7R4CI?page=2&amp;annotation=5CPNESYX" target="_self">2</a>)
As I see it a (maybe not fully realized) open source approach to artifact design.
<br>The number of makerspaces worldwide is growing rapidly: to date there are over 450 fab labs and 1000 active hackerspaces (FabLabs, 2015; HackerspaceWiki, 2015), listings that do not account for independent spaces. (<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="zotero://open-pdf/library/items/44X7R4CI?page=2&amp;annotation=S9RF8PV5" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="zotero:/open-pdf/library/items/44X7R4CI?page=2&amp;annotation=S9RF8PV5" target="_self">2</a>)<br>participatory backcasting (Mont et al., 2014). (<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="zotero://open-pdf/library/items/44X7R4CI?page=2&amp;annotation=UFT2SUPP" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="zotero:/open-pdf/library/items/44X7R4CI?page=2&amp;annotation=UFT2SUPP" target="_self">2</a>)<br> <img alt="Sources/kohtala2015a/attachments/kohtala2015a-3-x119-y489.png" src="sources/kohtala2015a/attachments/kohtala2015a-3-x119-y489.png" target="_self"> <img alt="Sources/kohtala2015a/attachments/kohtala2015a-4-x116-y53.png" src="sources/kohtala2015a/attachments/kohtala2015a-4-x116-y53.png" target="_self"><br>
other participants expressed sustainability concerns in 11% of all solutions while the sustain- ability faction did so in 6%. This seems to imply a comfort the sustainability group felt with expressing their environmental con- cerns in general trends but less certainty when it came to actual solutions in a makerspace. (<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="zotero://open-pdf/library/items/44X7R4CI?page=6&amp;annotation=9392VDU2" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="zotero:/open-pdf/library/items/44X7R4CI?page=6&amp;annotation=9392VDU2" target="_self">6</a>)<br> <img alt="Sources/kohtala2015a/attachments/kohtala2015a-6-x112-y55.png" src="sources/kohtala2015a/attachments/kohtala2015a-6-x112-y55.png" target="_self"><br>
only one solution expressed concern about how the makerspace receives its mate- rials: “Logistics of supplies” on a Sustainability post-it (<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="zotero://open-pdf/library/items/44X7R4CI?page=7&amp;annotation=5KLTPP4K" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="zotero:/open-pdf/library/items/44X7R4CI?page=7&amp;annotation=5KLTPP4K" target="_self">7</a>)<br>The asymmetries in sus- tainability expression are likely to have resulted from difficulties to concretise some visionary trends or conversely connect practical solutions to larger trends (<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="zotero://open-pdf/library/items/44X7R4CI?page=7&amp;annotation=ZPVBMRTP" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="zotero:/open-pdf/library/items/44X7R4CI?page=7&amp;annotation=ZPVBMRTP" target="_self">7</a>)<br>Only a few solutions addressed prevention of waste from the outset, as preferable to reuse (<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="zotero://open-pdf/library/items/44X7R4CI?page=9&amp;annotation=CYS57ITJ" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="zotero:/open-pdf/library/items/44X7R4CI?page=9&amp;annotation=CYS57ITJ" target="_self">9</a>)<br>There were also a significant number of solutions dedicated to energy issues among the Clearly Expressed issues: the deployment of renewable energy sources, the desire to make electricity con- sumption more visible and other solutions to reduce overall energy consumption (<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="zotero://open-pdf/library/items/44X7R4CI?page=9&amp;annotation=Q885R2NX" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="zotero:/open-pdf/library/items/44X7R4CI?page=9&amp;annotation=Q885R2NX" target="_self">9</a>)<br>The environmental attributes (or dangers) of the materials themselves, beyond dust and fumes, were little addressed by the participants. (<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="zotero://open-pdf/library/items/44X7R4CI?page=9&amp;annotation=5NDFMV2H" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="zotero:/open-pdf/library/items/44X7R4CI?page=9&amp;annotation=5NDFMV2H" target="_self">9</a>)<br>“hier- archy of good-bad materials on display (critical material thinking)” (<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="zotero://open-pdf/library/items/44X7R4CI?page=9&amp;annotation=SH9WLFKS" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="zotero:/open-pdf/library/items/44X7R4CI?page=9&amp;annotation=SH9WLFKS" target="_self">9</a>)<br>In the Clear Expression case, the sustainability faction seemed to be concerned with engaging the wider society in maker culture via repair activities, as well as engaging maker activists in “sustain- ability” via recycling infrastructures. The other participants showed more interest in the environmental issues in making activities themselves: dealing with the materials and the equipment, suggesting better fabbing processes and considering energy con- sumption. In waste prevention the sustainability group tended to focus on reuse, while the other participants offered solutions to combat waste and mistakes within the fabbing process itself, as well as pointing out the need for better (cleaner) materials in personal fabrication. (<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="zotero://open-pdf/library/items/44X7R4CI?page=9&amp;annotation=NN8AGV3P" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="zotero:/open-pdf/library/items/44X7R4CI?page=9&amp;annotation=NN8AGV3P" target="_self">9</a>)<br>The pro-environmental makers thus had limited engagement with unrecognised issues, and their engagement was also highly selective within this category: new materials and emerging tech- nologies did not draw their attention. Also elsewhere in the trend- solution mapping space, trends with clear sustainability implica- tions such as nano-technology, new material toxicity and changes in mass production were not addressed by the sustainability- oriented faction. (<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="zotero://open-pdf/library/items/44X7R4CI?page=9&amp;annotation=JUZGUTNU" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="zotero:/open-pdf/library/items/44X7R4CI?page=9&amp;annotation=JUZGUTNU" target="_self">9</a>)<br>The majority of the expressed issues did not have a clear envi- ronmental implication. Environmental sustainability thus does not appear to be an overarching aspect of all or even themajority ofissues the makers consider relevant in future makerspaces. (<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="zotero://open-pdf/library/items/44X7R4CI?page=10&amp;annotation=5CKA5HKT" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="zotero:/open-pdf/library/items/44X7R4CI?page=10&amp;annotation=5CKA5HKT" target="_self">10</a>)<br> <img alt="Sources/kohtala2015a/attachments/kohtala2015a-10-x105-y290.png" src="sources/kohtala2015a/attachments/kohtala2015a-10-x105-y290.png" target="_self">
The topics that participants expressed as relating to sustainabilit
focused especially on repair, reducing, reusing and recycling of ma
terials, electricity consumption and possibilities for more sustainabl<br>
materials and energy. (<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="zotero://open-pdf/library/items/44X7R4CI?page=11&amp;annotation=SF4YHYKB" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="zotero:/open-pdf/library/items/44X7R4CI?page=11&amp;annotation=SF4YHYKB" target="_self">11</a>)In contrast, trends with clear but unaddressed sustainabilit
implications related mainly to emerging topics of making such a
DIYbio, new materials such as nano based (Helland and Kastenholz
2008), new technologies and the overall implications of distribute<br>
manufacturing displacing mass production. (<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="zotero://open-pdf/library/items/44X7R4CI?page=11&amp;annotation=FD8N6XLW" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="zotero:/open-pdf/library/items/44X7R4CI?page=11&amp;annotation=FD8N6XLW" target="_self">11</a>)The toxicity of additiv
manufacturing materials was also weakly addressed by a singl
observation, even as this topic has been raised to the fore i<br>
research by Drizo and Pegna (2006) and Huang et al. (2013). (<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="zotero://open-pdf/library/items/44X7R4CI?page=11&amp;annotation=RXQ9X9AF" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="zotero:/open-pdf/library/items/44X7R4CI?page=11&amp;annotation=RXQ9X9AF" target="_self">11</a>)A ke
dynamic was that the more technical and future-oriented issue
were not at the focus of sustainability-oriented participants and th
rest of the participants did not pay systematic attention to thei<br>
potential environmental impacts (<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="zotero://open-pdf/library/items/44X7R4CI?page=11&amp;annotation=MGGA9WZX" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="zotero:/open-pdf/library/items/44X7R4CI?page=11&amp;annotation=MGGA9WZX" target="_self">11</a>)those competent and interested i
assessing environmental impacts were different people from thos
competent and interested in keeping track of rapidly evolving ne
technologies and materials for making. This gap in practitione<br>
orientation and competence is therefore potentially problematic (<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="zotero://open-pdf/library/items/44X7R4CI?page=11&amp;annotation=3T6IWBKP" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="zotero:/open-pdf/library/items/44X7R4CI?page=11&amp;annotation=3T6IWBKP" target="_self">11</a>)research objectives need to address these gaps i
sustainability orientation and competence among makers. There i
a clear need for targeted research on the environmental impacts o
personal fabrication technologies and materials, as well as real-lif<br>
maker practices (<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="zotero://open-pdf/library/items/44X7R4CI?page=11&amp;annotation=W7PDHD5E" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="zotero:/open-pdf/library/items/44X7R4CI?page=11&amp;annotation=W7PDHD5E" target="_self">11</a>)dialogue should be fostered between and amon
maker subcultures. Interaction and communication between pro
environmental and new-technology-oriented practitioners can b<br>
enhanced through shared spaces, workshops and conferences (<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="zotero://open-pdf/library/items/44X7R4CI?page=11&amp;annotation=LPBT9QXZ" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="zotero:/open-pdf/library/items/44X7R4CI?page=11&amp;annotation=LPBT9QXZ" target="_self">11</a>)guidance and solutions should be produced to bette
guide practitioners' everyday activities and the design of maker<br>
spaces. (<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="zotero://open-pdf/library/items/44X7R4CI?page=11&amp;annotation=HKPU7GA8" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="zotero:/open-pdf/library/items/44X7R4CI?page=11&amp;annotation=HKPU7GA8" target="_self">11</a>)According to the current findings, maker practitioners ar
less likely to succeed in addressing environmental impacts on thei
own to the extent they espouse. On the other hand, precisel
because makers like to represent themselves as environmentall
benign, such practical, concrete guidance is more likely to b
adopted, from manuals and checklists, to designs and solutions fo<br>
equipment, better recycling systems and the like (<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="zotero://open-pdf/library/items/44X7R4CI?page=11&amp;annotation=AJFME98N" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="zotero:/open-pdf/library/items/44X7R4CI?page=11&amp;annotation=AJFME98N" target="_self">11</a>)]]></description><link>sources/kohtala2015a/kohtala2015a.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Sources/kohtala2015a/kohtala2015a.md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 25 Jul 2025 11:11:13 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="sources/kohtala2015a/attachments/kohtala2015a-3-x119-y489.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;sources/kohtala2015a/attachments/kohtala2015a-3-x119-y489.png&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Sources]]></title><description><![CDATA[
<a data-href="kara2022" href="sources/kara2022/kara2022.html#_0" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">kara2022</a>
<br><a data-href="kohtala2015" href="sources/kohtala2015/kohtala2015.html#_0" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">kohtala2015</a>
<br><a data-href="kohtala2015a" href="sources/kohtala2015a/kohtala2015a.html#_0" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">kohtala2015a</a>
]]></description><link>sources/sources.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Sources/Sources.md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 25 Jul 2025 11:11:08 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[triple bottom line]]></title><description><![CDATA[People, Planet, Profit"In most instances, sustainability is shown in the middle supported by all three elements as enablers. These models have emerged to be one of the most dominant forms of explaining sustainability and sustainable development framework over the past three decades and are frequently used in literature, online works, business models and documentation of sustainability, and they were the foundation of the triple bottom line concept for corporate sustainability" (<a data-href="kara2022" href="sources/kara2022/kara2022.html#_0" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">kara2022</a>)<br><img alt="kara2022-2-x295-y305.png" src="sources/kara2022/attachments/kara2022-2-x295-y305.png" target="_self"><br><a data-href="kara2022" href="sources/kara2022/kara2022.html#_0" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">kara2022</a>]]></description><link>terms/triple-bottom-line.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Terms/triple bottom line.md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 25 Jul 2025 11:10:58 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="sources/kara2022/attachments/kara2022-2-x295-y305.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;sources/kara2022/attachments/kara2022-2-x295-y305.png&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[sustainability]]></title><link>terms/sustainability.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Terms/sustainability.md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 25 Jul 2025 08:54:10 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[kara2022-2-x295-y305]]></title><description><![CDATA[<img src="sources/kara2022/attachments/kara2022-2-x295-y305.png" target="_self">]]></description><link>sources/kara2022/attachments/kara2022-2-x295-y305.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Sources/kara2022/attachments/kara2022-2-x295-y305.png</guid><pubDate>Fri, 25 Jul 2025 08:51:57 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="sources/kara2022/attachments/kara2022-2-x295-y305.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;sources/kara2022/attachments/kara2022-2-x295-y305.png&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[kohtala2015-8-x42-y56]]></title><description><![CDATA[<img src="sources/kohtala2015/attachments/kohtala2015-8-x42-y56.png" target="_self">]]></description><link>sources/kohtala2015/attachments/kohtala2015-8-x42-y56.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Sources/kohtala2015/attachments/kohtala2015-8-x42-y56.png</guid><pubDate>Fri, 25 Jul 2025 08:51:33 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="sources/kohtala2015/attachments/kohtala2015-8-x42-y56.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;sources/kohtala2015/attachments/kohtala2015-8-x42-y56.png&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[kohtala2015-8-x311-y67]]></title><description><![CDATA[<img src="sources/kohtala2015/attachments/kohtala2015-8-x311-y67.png" target="_self">]]></description><link>sources/kohtala2015/attachments/kohtala2015-8-x311-y67.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Sources/kohtala2015/attachments/kohtala2015-8-x311-y67.png</guid><pubDate>Fri, 25 Jul 2025 08:51:33 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="sources/kohtala2015/attachments/kohtala2015-8-x311-y67.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;sources/kohtala2015/attachments/kohtala2015-8-x311-y67.png&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[kohtala2015-12-x309-y71]]></title><description><![CDATA[<img src="sources/kohtala2015/attachments/kohtala2015-12-x309-y71.png" target="_self">]]></description><link>sources/kohtala2015/attachments/kohtala2015-12-x309-y71.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Sources/kohtala2015/attachments/kohtala2015-12-x309-y71.png</guid><pubDate>Fri, 25 Jul 2025 08:51:33 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="sources/kohtala2015/attachments/kohtala2015-12-x309-y71.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;sources/kohtala2015/attachments/kohtala2015-12-x309-y71.png&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[kohtala2015-3-x43-y94]]></title><description><![CDATA[<img src="sources/kohtala2015/attachments/kohtala2015-3-x43-y94.png" target="_self">]]></description><link>sources/kohtala2015/attachments/kohtala2015-3-x43-y94.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Sources/kohtala2015/attachments/kohtala2015-3-x43-y94.png</guid><pubDate>Fri, 25 Jul 2025 08:51:33 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="sources/kohtala2015/attachments/kohtala2015-3-x43-y94.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;sources/kohtala2015/attachments/kohtala2015-3-x43-y94.png&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[personal fabrication]]></title><link>terms/personal-fabrication.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Terms/personal fabrication.md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 25 Jul 2025 08:40:33 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[artifacts]]></title><link>terms/artifacts.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Terms/artifacts.md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 25 Jul 2025 08:23:52 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[kohtala2015a-6-x112-y55]]></title><description><![CDATA[<img src="sources/kohtala2015a/attachments/kohtala2015a-6-x112-y55.png" target="_self">]]></description><link>sources/kohtala2015a/attachments/kohtala2015a-6-x112-y55.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Sources/kohtala2015a/attachments/kohtala2015a-6-x112-y55.png</guid><pubDate>Fri, 25 Jul 2025 07:21:56 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="sources/kohtala2015a/attachments/kohtala2015a-6-x112-y55.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;sources/kohtala2015a/attachments/kohtala2015a-6-x112-y55.png&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[kohtala2015a-10-x105-y290]]></title><description><![CDATA[<img src="sources/kohtala2015a/attachments/kohtala2015a-10-x105-y290.png" target="_self">]]></description><link>sources/kohtala2015a/attachments/kohtala2015a-10-x105-y290.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Sources/kohtala2015a/attachments/kohtala2015a-10-x105-y290.png</guid><pubDate>Fri, 25 Jul 2025 07:21:56 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="sources/kohtala2015a/attachments/kohtala2015a-10-x105-y290.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;sources/kohtala2015a/attachments/kohtala2015a-10-x105-y290.png&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[kohtala2015a-3-x119-y489]]></title><description><![CDATA[<img src="sources/kohtala2015a/attachments/kohtala2015a-3-x119-y489.png" target="_self">]]></description><link>sources/kohtala2015a/attachments/kohtala2015a-3-x119-y489.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Sources/kohtala2015a/attachments/kohtala2015a-3-x119-y489.png</guid><pubDate>Fri, 25 Jul 2025 07:21:56 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="sources/kohtala2015a/attachments/kohtala2015a-3-x119-y489.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;sources/kohtala2015a/attachments/kohtala2015a-3-x119-y489.png&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[kohtala2015a-4-x116-y53]]></title><description><![CDATA[<img src="sources/kohtala2015a/attachments/kohtala2015a-4-x116-y53.png" target="_self">]]></description><link>sources/kohtala2015a/attachments/kohtala2015a-4-x116-y53.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Sources/kohtala2015a/attachments/kohtala2015a-4-x116-y53.png</guid><pubDate>Fri, 25 Jul 2025 07:21:56 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="sources/kohtala2015a/attachments/kohtala2015a-4-x116-y53.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;sources/kohtala2015a/attachments/kohtala2015a-4-x116-y53.png&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[open-source appropriate technologies]]></title><description><![CDATA[is appropriate technology developed through the principles of the open-design movement. Appropriate technology is technology designed with special consideration for the environmental, ethical, cultural, social, political, and economic aspects of the community it is intended for. Open design is public and licensed to allow it to be used, modified, and distributed freely.Frome <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Open-source_appropriate_technology" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Open-source_appropriate_technology" target="_self">wikipedia</a>, accessed 24-07-2025]]></description><link>terms/open-source-appropriate-technologies.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Terms/open-source appropriate technologies.md</guid><pubDate>Thu, 24 Jul 2025 12:07:16 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[appropriate technology]]></title><description><![CDATA[is a movement (and its manifestations) encompassing technological choice and application that is small-scale, affordable by its users, labor-intensive, energy-efficient, environmentally sustainable, and locally autonomous. It was originally articulated as intermediate technology by the economist Ernst Friedrich "Fritz" Schumacher in his work Small Is Beautiful. Both Schumacher and many modern-day proponents of appropriate technology also emphasize the technology as people-centered.From <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Appropriate_technology" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Appropriate_technology" target="_self">wikipedia</a>, accessed 24-07-2025]]></description><link>terms/appropriate-technology.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Terms/appropriate technology.md</guid><pubDate>Thu, 24 Jul 2025 12:06:24 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[grassroots innovation]]></title><description><![CDATA[is the voluntary generation and development of innovations by any member of an organization, regardless of function or seniority.It is considered a form of bottom-up innovation, whereby innovation resides 'deep in the bowels' of an organization, i.e., it is seen as a responsibility of all members of an organization. From <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Grassroots_innovation" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Grassroots_innovation" target="_self">wikipedia</a>, accessed 24-07-2025]]></description><link>terms/grassroots-innovation.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Terms/grassroots innovation.md</guid><pubDate>Thu, 24 Jul 2025 12:06:21 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[leapfrogging]]></title><description><![CDATA[Leapfrogging is a concept used in many domains of the economics and business fields, and was originally developed in the area of industrial organization and economic growth. The main idea behind the concept of leapfrogging is that small and incremental innovations lead a dominant firm to stay ahead. However, sometimes, radical innovations will permit new firms to leapfrog the ancient and dominant firm. From <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Leapfrogging" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Leapfrogging" target="_self">wikipedia</a>, accessed 24-07-2025]]></description><link>terms/leapfrogging.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Terms/leapfrogging.md</guid><pubDate>Thu, 24 Jul 2025 12:06:11 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>